[SPEAKER_00]: Once you're physically secluded from from company, from others, a practice of of some reflexive questioning can really take take root.
[SPEAKER_00]: Because there's a... there's a difference between how... how we feel when we are alone and how we feel in the proximity of other people.
[SPEAKER_00]: There's a fundamental existential difference.
[SPEAKER_00]: And that's why that type of solitude is necessary for, eh... for any kind of meditation that leads to understanding.
[SPEAKER_00]: Any kind of meditation that it's not about
[SPEAKER_00]: It's not about shutting out the world of senses, but it's about fully understanding it.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, the reflexive questioning, it's more of an attitude towards your own mind, than it is an actual questioning and looking for answers.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, once we're alone, quiet, calm, you can just ask yourself, what is the mind thinking right now?
[SPEAKER_00]: But, the point is, don't give the answers right away.
[SPEAKER_00]: Don't jump at answering and feel this or it's thinking this.
[SPEAKER_00]: Just use the question as, eh... as directing your own attention towards the context in which your mind is.
[SPEAKER_00]: Not towards the particular... particular thoughts you might be thinking.
[SPEAKER_00]: And then, let that context endure.
[SPEAKER_00]: Let that question... let that direction revealed by question endure.
[SPEAKER_00]: Because it's not really
[SPEAKER_00]: About the content of the answer, it's about discerning the context behind it.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, what is the mind thinking right now, while this talk is being listened to, while you're seated, while you're alone?
[SPEAKER_00]: What is in the background of that?
[SPEAKER_00]: What thoughts?
[SPEAKER_00]: What moods?
[SPEAKER_00]: And learn how to see them in that background, on the level of that background, without overdoing their analysis or rationalizing.
[SPEAKER_00]: But you want to see them as well, because by not seeing them and not rationalizing them, you'll be mystifying it.
[SPEAKER_00]: You don't want that either.
[SPEAKER_00]: You want to see it on its own terms.
[SPEAKER_00]: And its own terms are terms of the background and a degree of ambiguity and less of the particular clarity.
[SPEAKER_00]: That's just the nature of those fundamental thoughts that determine your mood, that then determine your particular actions and so on.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, what thoughts are present right now?
[SPEAKER_00]: You let that endure.
[SPEAKER_00]: Did the mind start slipping away?
[SPEAKER_00]: If the mind starts slipping away, you find something more defined to think about.
[SPEAKER_00]: As in, what are my thoughts right now?
[SPEAKER_00]: How am I feeling right now, in regard to those thoughts?
[SPEAKER_00]: What is my fundamental mood?
[SPEAKER_00]: What is my experience as a whole?
[SPEAKER_00]: Am I feeling it pleasantly or unpleasantly?
[SPEAKER_00]: Am I aware of my situation right now that I'm in?
[SPEAKER_00]: So, whatever thoughts might be coming up, for example, you might be concerned about not being able to maintain sufficient solitude.
[SPEAKER_00]: Or you might be concerned that you might lose the track of your mind once you get out of the solitude.
[SPEAKER_00]: Then, you start looking into that further.
[SPEAKER_00]: Why are you concerned with the loss of this particular composure?
[SPEAKER_00]: What is concerning about that?
[SPEAKER_00]: There is no right or wrong answer.
[SPEAKER_00]: You just want to see what's behind it, what's behind that concern, hence the question.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, initially, you might have to be holding yourself back a bit in terms of trying to formulate the answer and learning how to see behind the question.
[SPEAKER_00]: But, in order to see behind the question, questioning is necessary for that.
[SPEAKER_00]: And that's why you need to know what question should be asked.
[SPEAKER_00]: And in this case, the question is, why would I be affected by the loss of composure in the mind?
[SPEAKER_00]: So far, based on my experience throughout this life, this mind of mine, do I have any say in its changing?
[SPEAKER_00]: Do I have any say in its deciding this or that?
[SPEAKER_00]: You realize there is only a relative amount of say.
[SPEAKER_00]: Overall, you are kind of subjected to the weathers of your mind, to the moods, basically.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, why are you subjected to something that you are not in control of?
[SPEAKER_00]: Again, don't answer it.
[SPEAKER_00]: Ask the question and let it endure.
[SPEAKER_00]: Let it endure for a whole day, if you need to.
[SPEAKER_00]: The whole point is allowing things to endure on the level of these moods and discernments of nature of things.
[SPEAKER_00]: You're not concerned with a particular content.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, why are you subjected to something that you are not in control of, that you are not the subject of?
[SPEAKER_00]: So, the mind has its own moods.
[SPEAKER_00]: arises, ceases, either way, it endures one way or the other.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yet, you are the one that's seemingly being affected by it, by the unpleasant mood, by the pleasant mood.
[SPEAKER_00]: You might be affected now with a concern of losing solitude or or not being able to to maintain the composure when you go back into the world.
[SPEAKER_00]: Why is that?
[SPEAKER_00]: Why is the loss of composure a worry?
[SPEAKER_00]: Because you might do something unwholesome?
[SPEAKER_00]: Why is doing something unwholesome troubling you?
[SPEAKER_00]: Because it will fill you with remorse or similar?
[SPEAKER_00]: Why is remorse a problem?
[SPEAKER_00]: Because it's unpleasant.
[SPEAKER_00]: And, above all, because it's not in your control.
[SPEAKER_00]: If we were in control, we would never be remorseful, or sad, or unhappy, or disappointed.
[SPEAKER_00]: We just wouldn't.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, really, the problem here is that you're subjected to these things of your own mind, of your own doing, in a way, but you are not in control and that's...
[SPEAKER_00]: So, when you are subjected to the disagreeable, that is your suffering then.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, bottom line is then, you don't want to lose composure, you're afraid of compromising solitude, that might compromise composure, that might compromise the currently agreeable state of mind.
[SPEAKER_00]: But if currently agreeable state of mind were yours to begin with, it would not change.
[SPEAKER_00]: It would stay for as long as you want it to stay.
[SPEAKER_00]: And you always want to stay.
[SPEAKER_00]: Nobody wants disagreeable.
[SPEAKER_00]: And even if people want disagreeable things, it's because they find that agreeable.
[SPEAKER_00]: That's just the most fundamental motivation, pleasure, be it happiness or peace.
[SPEAKER_00]: Anyway, point is agreeable.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, then, all these doubts you might have, fears, worries about this, about that, about what if I lose my mindfulness and then I say things that then I regret to, or I do things, or what if this piece doesn't last as long as I want.
[SPEAKER_00]: All of these concerns, all these particular proliferations, possibilities of these concerns, are all rooted in one one thing that is here, right now, with you.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, if that is then the problem, in all these particular things you might be worrying about, how can you uproot it?
[SPEAKER_00]: Or rather, what would be the better way of going about it?
[SPEAKER_00]: So, if
[SPEAKER_00]: Losing solitude worries you, because you might cause suffering.
[SPEAKER_00]: Losing your mindfulness worries you, because you might result in suffering.
[SPEAKER_00]: Doing things, saying things, thinking things, worry you, because you might cause suffering.
[SPEAKER_00]: Which is a better way to go, in order to try to understand this and overcome that issue?
[SPEAKER_00]: Would it be
[SPEAKER_00]: Would it be trying to protect your solitude?
[SPEAKER_00]: Would it be trying forcefully or with full determination to never lose your mindfulness?
[SPEAKER_00]: Would it be never saying or doing anything that might upset anyone?
[SPEAKER_00]: Or, would it be freeing yourself from possibility to suffer in regard to loss of control?
[SPEAKER_00]: In regard to anything, which is more likely to pertain to the actual freedom from suffering, trying to manage things particularly, trying to protect your environment, trying to deal with it, trying to deal with remorse, with things that come as a result of you losing your control or losing the sight of it, or understanding
[SPEAKER_00]: What's in common to all these things, which is you not wanting pain of any kind.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, then, the question should be asked is, am I right in gratuitously assuming the attitude of not wanting this pleasure?
[SPEAKER_00]: Am I right in taking it for granted?
[SPEAKER_00]: Am I right in holding it?
[SPEAKER_00]: Am I right in maintaining it?
[SPEAKER_00]: Do I have a right to do so?
[SPEAKER_00]: Because attitude towards the possibility of a disagreeable feeling does imply a certain entitlement from your point of view.
[SPEAKER_00]: You think you have a right to have a say.
[SPEAKER_00]: But is that really the case?
[SPEAKER_00]: Because if you had a say in the first place, you wouldn't need to be wanting anything.
[SPEAKER_00]: Things would just obey your command, your control, your will.
[SPEAKER_00]: But they don't.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, you thinking you have a say in the first place, it's actually secondary to the things themselves.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yet, you thinking you have a say, kind of puts you first.
[SPEAKER_00]: And it's that very discrepancy that is the root of all the suffering.
[SPEAKER_00]: Absolutely nothing else.
[SPEAKER_00]: The Buddha said... well, he never said that suffering is caused because of this, or because of that, or because somebody done something disagreeable, or we didn't get enough of agreeable, or... All these things are manifestations of suffering, but suffering, in itself,
[SPEAKER_00]: It's entirely, completely rooted in craving.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, presence of craving, presence of that discrepancy that I'm talking about, means presence of suffering.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, if then, the discrepancy is removed, would you be able to suffer, even if things do appear as disagreeable?
[SPEAKER_00]: So, that's the important distinction here.
[SPEAKER_00]: Everybody who read the suttas would say, yes, craving is suffering.
[SPEAKER_00]: But it's actually... the point is discerning the tacit attitude that everybody has in still assuming that say in things.
[SPEAKER_00]: And by that, I mean say towards the
[SPEAKER_00]: Like present enduring feeling, you have a say in it, by wanting it or not wanting it.
[SPEAKER_00]: Now, practically, you know the feeling doesn't obey your will whatsoever, but that doesn't stop you from still maintaining that assumption that it should.
[SPEAKER_00]: And that assumption is maintained through carelessly, eh... holding on an attitude of
[SPEAKER_00]: Not wanting pain.
[SPEAKER_00]: Wanting to get rid of the arisen pain.
[SPEAKER_00]: And the attitude of wanting to prolong the arisen pleasure.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, it's fine to not want pain.
[SPEAKER_00]: But what it's not fine is that within the present enduring feeling, whatever that feeling is, to maintain that stance that creates the discrepancy.
[SPEAKER_00]: In pleasure, you want more.
[SPEAKER_00]: Hence the discrepancy.
[SPEAKER_00]: Hence the suffering.
[SPEAKER_00]: In pain, you want less.
[SPEAKER_00]: You want the absence of it.
[SPEAKER_00]: But it's present.
[SPEAKER_00]: But you... your attitude is attitude of wanting it to go.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, that's another discrepancy.
[SPEAKER_00]: And practically, those are the two feelings one can be practicing in regard to.
[SPEAKER_00]: There is obviously the neutral feeling as well.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's slightly harder to discern, but even within that, you can, because when it's neither pleasant nor unpleasant, what the mind wants is distraction from that neutral presence.
[SPEAKER_00]: Hence, the discrepancy, hence the suffering.
[SPEAKER_00]: That's why Buddha said that neutral feeling, if it's not known, it's felt unpleasantly.
[SPEAKER_00]: And you create a discrepancy when you don't know that you couldn't have created it in the first place.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, this is how every meditation should go.
[SPEAKER_00]: For yourself, secluded, contemplating rightly, asking the right questions, and then letting the direction revealed by those questions endure.
[SPEAKER_00]: Don't jump into answers, but don't over-mystify and turn it into a brain fog.
[SPEAKER_00]: You're after clarity, clarity of understanding.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, through thinking about nature of suffering, you get closer to understanding it.
[SPEAKER_00]: You get closer in seeing that your concern with particular things that bother you is not your suffering.
[SPEAKER_00]: The suffering is the presence of the discrepancy that you created in regard to things that bother you or in regard to things that don't bother you.
[SPEAKER_00]: Because can you remain indifferent in regard to pleasure, in regard to happiness, in regard to possibility of pleasure and happiness?
[SPEAKER_00]: Will your mind not remain, not become elated towards it?
[SPEAKER_00]: Will your mind not want more of it?
[SPEAKER_00]: Will your mind try not to make it stay forever?
[SPEAKER_00]: Can you remain imperturb... imperturbable?
[SPEAKER_00]: Can you remain imperturbable in regard to pleasure?
[SPEAKER_00]: Or can you remain imperturbable in regard to pain?
[SPEAKER_00]: Can you remain mindful and composed in regard to neutral feeling?
[SPEAKER_00]: Or will your mind turn and find something to do that will distract itself from itself?
[SPEAKER_00]: So, if the answer is yes, then you wonder, so what do I do?
[SPEAKER_00]: What you do is keep bringing back into the mind these very things, because it's... it's the very ignoring of these truths and characteristics of... of... of the... behind the motivations of your actions.
[SPEAKER_00]: That's how you maintain them.
[SPEAKER_00]: And you ignore them, when you not see them.
[SPEAKER_00]: And you not see them, because you ignore them.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, it's a vicious circle.
[SPEAKER_00]: But if you start looking at least in that direction, through asking yourself the right questions, for the sake of revealing the direction behind it, then you're ignoring it less and less.
[SPEAKER_00]: And eventually, you will become unable to ignore it.
[SPEAKER_00]: Why?
[SPEAKER_00]: Because it's the universal truth.
[SPEAKER_00]: The dhamma.
[SPEAKER_00]: That's what Buddha said himself.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's not a creation of a theory or something.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's just revealing the nature of things that are there.
[SPEAKER_00]: Whether you want them or not makes no difference.
[SPEAKER_00]: And through understanding the right nature, for which you need to have that right instruction, hence the right questions, then you will be unable to maintain all the discrepancy, all the sense of... sense of control and mastery of things, all the gratuitous notions of I have a say or... or I at least imply.
[SPEAKER_00]: Having a say through my attitude, in regard to what I'm feeling right now.
[SPEAKER_00]: So then, whether it's pleasure, pain, neutral feeling, there will be no discrepancy maintained by the mind in regard to it.
[SPEAKER_00]: And if there is no discrepancy, there's no suffering.
[SPEAKER_00]: And there is in the scene, there is just a scene, in the herd, there's just a herd, and so on for all the senses, as that Bhagya Sutta says.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, what is my mind thinking right now?
[SPEAKER_00]: You can ask yourself that.
[SPEAKER_00]: The answer is... if the answer is nothing specifically, that's fine.
[SPEAKER_00]: That's the reason experience as a whole.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, what are the background thoughts present in regard to your non-specific thinking right here, right now?
[SPEAKER_00]: What's at the back of your mind?
[SPEAKER_00]: Don't try to make it to the front.
[SPEAKER_00]: Just see it at the back, but see it.
[SPEAKER_00]: What's in that distance?
[SPEAKER_00]: Through that ambiguous fog.
[SPEAKER_00]: What is it?
[SPEAKER_00]: What is it thinking?
[SPEAKER_00]: It's going to be a general, ambiguous thought.
[SPEAKER_00]: Don't over-define it again, but don't ignore it either.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, if you don't know how to relate to it, see how it feels.
[SPEAKER_00]: How are you feeling in regard to that thought?
[SPEAKER_00]: At the background of your mind.
[SPEAKER_00]: Oh, at the background of your mind, there is a certain discomfort because of the, eh...
[SPEAKER_00]: Implicit pressure of the duties that I have to do in couple of hours time.
[SPEAKER_00]: To go to work, I have to do this, I have to do that.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, that's it.
[SPEAKER_00]: The Bhagavad-gītā.
[SPEAKER_00]: You're not thinking about it, but it's kind of there.
[SPEAKER_00]: And you could see that that... that's being... that state of mind, that mood is being felt.
[SPEAKER_00]: And it's perceived in that ambiguous domain.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, what you want to do is, without trying to over-define it, you want to learn how to allow that, eh... discernment, that recognition to endure.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, you recognized that there is a certain amount of discomfort in the background of your mind, because of something you don't want to do, but you have to do.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, that's fine.
[SPEAKER_00]: But it's... through not seeing it,
[SPEAKER_00]: You immediately default, or rather, by not seeing it, the starting point, the first attitude towards something that's not seen, is not wanting it, if it's disagreeable, and wanting it, if it's agreeable.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's the discrepancy we talked about.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, now you're discerning that, in the background of your mind, there is... so, you don't have to, like, overly psychologize it.
[SPEAKER_00]: You don't have to rationalize it and explain to yourself how duties must be performed.
[SPEAKER_00]: None of that is questioned here.
[SPEAKER_00]: None of that is a problem here.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah, we all must perform duties.
[SPEAKER_00]: We all have things to do.
[SPEAKER_00]: The point is, your attitude in regard to it, on the level of that background, on the level at the back of your mind, where you're not used to thinking about things, you only think about things that are in front of you,
[SPEAKER_00]: And in order to think about something, you need to bring it to the front, which means you're then not seeing these little ambiguous general backgrounds and moods that are actually more fundamental than your particular thoughts.
[SPEAKER_00]: They are fuel... they are sort of directing you, like... like the wind gently blowing into the sails.
[SPEAKER_00]: It might not be a very discernible or strong wind, but the point is, there is a constant exertion of its pressure against the sail.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, you will be moving the way it directs you.
[SPEAKER_00]: And as the Buddha said, the fundamental reason for being directed by this discrepancy, by the greed aversion, is ignoring it, ignorance of it.
[SPEAKER_00]: Not... not having it seen,
[SPEAKER_00]: Not seeing it, not having it seen, not discerning it, not allowing it to endure in that and develop clarity in regard to it.
[SPEAKER_00]: And when I say clarity, I don't mean to rationalize it and to collect the data about it.
[SPEAKER_00]: That's all secondary to it.
[SPEAKER_00]: Clarity means whenever you look at the background, you will see it.
[SPEAKER_00]: You don't have to spend half an hour contemplating, preparing yourself.
[SPEAKER_00]: Basically, it will.
[SPEAKER_00]: You will see these things.
[SPEAKER_00]: And how you develop that?
[SPEAKER_00]: You develop it through trying to see it, through clarifying the meaning, the context, by clarifying the nature of it.
[SPEAKER_00]: And then, if the mind is more composed, and you have that clarity in regard to the present, enduring feeling of discomfort,
[SPEAKER_00]: Because of the pressure of duties and things you don't want to do in two hours' time.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, did you create that feeling?
[SPEAKER_00]: Did it come from you, that feeling of discomfort?
[SPEAKER_00]: No.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, you found it there.
[SPEAKER_00]: Through looking at the background perception, so to speak, you discerned there is discomfort there.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, you found it there, which means it was already there on its own.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, if something was already there on its own, you haven't created it.
[SPEAKER_00]: You can't even conceive where it came from, as in, oh, it's because of this and this and this.
[SPEAKER_00]: You just found it there.
[SPEAKER_00]: Now, you might rationalize that it's because of this, this, this, but all that is secondary to the independent presence, present enduring of that feeling of discomfort in regard to the duties that you have to perform in two hours time.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, if something is just found there, independent of you, its origins pretty much inconceivable to you.
[SPEAKER_00]: Are you justified in having the attitude of wanting it to go away?
[SPEAKER_00]: So, out of the two of you, you and that disagreeable discomfort, who is more right, basically, to be there?
[SPEAKER_00]: Whose attitude is more correct?
[SPEAKER_00]: The attitude of that discomfort of a feeling, that's just discomfort, that doesn't want to do some work, or is it you feeling entitled to not want it?
[SPEAKER_00]: Who out of two of you is not minding their own business?
[SPEAKER_00]: Clearly, that feeling is.
[SPEAKER_00]: Because it's unaware of you.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, then, it's you who is not minding your own business.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's you who interferes with disagreeable.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's you who interferes with agreeable.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's you who interferes with neutral.
[SPEAKER_00]: Why is that?
[SPEAKER_00]: Because you haven't fully realized that you can't interfere in the first place.
[SPEAKER_00]: That the interference cannot change the nature of things.
[SPEAKER_00]: Presence of interference means presence of suffering.
[SPEAKER_00]: The nature of things remains the same.
[SPEAKER_00]: Absence of interference means absence of suffering.
[SPEAKER_00]: Five aggregates are five aggregates.
[SPEAKER_00]: Puputujana or foranarhana.
[SPEAKER_00]: It doesn't matter.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's the same.
[SPEAKER_00]: The difference is the assumption in regard to it.
[SPEAKER_00]: And that's all a person needs to do, really.
[SPEAKER_00]: Great revelation or secret revealed and they will then result in freedom of the mind.
[SPEAKER_00]: No.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's just learning how to stop ignoring the fundamental characteristics, the nature of things, of your feelings, your perceptions, your moods, your intentions.
[SPEAKER_00]: That's it.
[SPEAKER_00]: There is no like a perfect set of perceptions and feelings you you you develop bit by bit and then it kind of culminates in this great great manifestation.
[SPEAKER_00]: No, it's actually undoing your perception, because everybody starts as a puthujjana.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, puthujjana cannot, on the basis of puthujjana, build his arahantship.
[SPEAKER_00]: Puthujjana can become an arahant by undoing his state of puthujjana.
[SPEAKER_00]: Hence, it's... it's, eh... individually, to be known by the wise, internally, by undoing yourself, basically.
[SPEAKER_00]: And that's why nobody can do that for you.
[SPEAKER_00]: And you undo things, you undo these gratuitous attitudes and notions that result directly in your suffering, through understanding them, through discerning them.
[SPEAKER_00]: Why?
[SPEAKER_00]: Because
[SPEAKER_00]: The basis for their existence is being ignored.
[SPEAKER_00]: That's what a vijja is.
[SPEAKER_00]: And you ignore something for various reasons, but the point is, it's being ignored.
[SPEAKER_00]: You ignore something through giving in gratuitously, through greed, aversion, delusion, which are all results, secondary results, to that discrepancy that your attitude fundamentally creates.
[SPEAKER_00]: But now, obviously, through taking for granted the results of that discrepancy, you carry on the discrepancy.
[SPEAKER_00]: That's why... that's why the sensory strain needs to come first.
[SPEAKER_00]: That we have to stop engaging with greed, aversion, delusion, in order then to discern the attitude behind it.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, if you can ask yourself now, has your mood changed?
[SPEAKER_00]: Has your mood changed?
[SPEAKER_00]: Whatever is being felt before?
[SPEAKER_00]: Is it still the same thing enduring there?
[SPEAKER_00]: Now, you might say, oh, it's slightly different, but overall it's the same.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, it's the same thing.
[SPEAKER_00]: And we gave the example of, say, that discomfort because of something you have to do after this.
[SPEAKER_00]: Does it bother you?
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah, discomfort, it's discomfortable in itself, but does it bother you?
[SPEAKER_00]: Does it bother you now, when you have looked at it, when you've seen it, when you've discerned it in the background?
[SPEAKER_00]: It might bother you, but does it bother you as much as before?
[SPEAKER_00]: Do you feel that pressure exercised over you to the same extent as it was when you were not aware, or rather turning a blind eye towards that which was pressuring you?
[SPEAKER_00]: No, it cannot.
[SPEAKER_00]: It cannot exercise the same pressure.
[SPEAKER_00]: That's the most
[SPEAKER_00]: A direct release of the pressure, a direct, immediate, instantaneous release of the burden.
[SPEAKER_00]: Now, you might forget about it, and it comes back, but that's fine.
[SPEAKER_00]: That's just how it works.
[SPEAKER_00]: Repeating the motions of discerning the nature of things rightly, they will result in you not maintaining that discrepancy in regard to discomfort or comfort.
[SPEAKER_00]: You are gradually releasing that pressure that's being exercised over you.
[SPEAKER_00]: That's why there is no greater verification of understanding than freedom from suffering.
[SPEAKER_00]: That's why that's the only verification you need.
[SPEAKER_00]: Even if the whole world comes and says that that's wrong, you know that through direct understanding of that, you are unable to suffer.
[SPEAKER_00]: And that's what the Buddha meant in the suttas, that the one with the right view, even if everybody comes and tells him, no, the Buddha was completely wrong, his mind will remain unchanged, because even, like, no matter what they would say, that person, for oneself, is directly incapable of suffering.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's not like running away from it, or pretend it's not there, or having to maintain some determined meditation technique to never suffer.
[SPEAKER_00]: No.
[SPEAKER_00]: He fully understood that he's incapable of suffering amidst the suffering.
[SPEAKER_00]: Whatever he does, doesn't matter.
[SPEAKER_00]: He cannot suffer.
[SPEAKER_00]: And there is absolutely... you cannot ask for a better reward and verification that things have been done rightly.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, that's the criteria.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, all this questioning should be resulting in freeing you from suffering.
[SPEAKER_00]: Not through ignoring, not through turning a blind eye, not through trying to shut things out, but through actually discerning the nature of them on the right level, the level of that background, the level of the mood, the level of the feeling.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, if the disagreeable feeling that we gave as an example is still there, it's still enduring, you can start looking at its characteristics.
[SPEAKER_00]: It is minding its own business, isn't it?
[SPEAKER_00]: Whether you think about it or not, doesn't matter.
[SPEAKER_00]: That feeling is there, enduring.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, you are the one
[SPEAKER_00]: Who makes oneself bother with it?
[SPEAKER_00]: Through not seeing it.
[SPEAKER_00]: Through not allowing it to endure.
[SPEAKER_00]: Through giving in gratuitously to the notion of... to be get rid of.
[SPEAKER_00]: And when that general feeling, whatever it was, changes, you'll find a different feeling there.
[SPEAKER_00]: You won't see a moment in between the change.
[SPEAKER_00]: You're just going to now look and see, oh, the disagreeable feeling is gone, which means now, automatically, something is agreeable.
[SPEAKER_00]: You don't care about what is agreeable, you look at the feeling.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, it doesn't matter, oh, it's agreeable because of this, this and this, or it's disagreeable because of this and this.
[SPEAKER_00]: What matters is,
[SPEAKER_00]: Is there agreeable feeling enduring?
[SPEAKER_00]: Or is there a disagreeable feeling enduring?
[SPEAKER_00]: And that's it.
[SPEAKER_00]: There's no need for a further answer.
[SPEAKER_00]: Let that question that has revealed direction of the whatever feeling is enduring right there, let it endure, because through allowing it to endure, you're allowing it... well, you're allowing yourself to see its nature, which is
[SPEAKER_00]: Independent of you, you're not in its control.
[SPEAKER_00]: You cannot own it even if you want to.
[SPEAKER_00]: And above all, you are entirely invisible to it.
[SPEAKER_00]: You don't exist for feelings.
[SPEAKER_00]: You don't exist for intentions.
[SPEAKER_00]: You don't exist for perceptions.
[SPEAKER_00]: You exist because you assume your own existence.
[SPEAKER_00]: That's why upādāna manifests power, the being.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, the five aggregates, if you're completely invisible to form, feeling, perception, intentions and consciousness, where is any room for your sense of self?
[SPEAKER_00]: Because when you have a thought of me, myself, that has appeared.
[SPEAKER_00]: That's one of the aggregates, that thought.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, if your thought of your sense of self cannot see you,
[SPEAKER_00]: You're invisible to it.
[SPEAKER_00]: You realize that your own sense of self is something that cannot be yours.
[SPEAKER_00]: It doesn't care about you.
[SPEAKER_00]: And that's what anatta really means.
[SPEAKER_00]: That self, which I've been taking to be mine, is not mine.
[SPEAKER_00]: That's how it becomes not-self.
[SPEAKER_00]: But the thing that was self before and now it's not-self is still there.
[SPEAKER_00]: The Buddha never said there is no self, there is not such thing.
[SPEAKER_00]: No, he said it's the five aggregates that are taken as self.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, the thing that is yourself is one of the aggregates.
[SPEAKER_00]: Whatever that aggregate is at the time, doesn't matter.
[SPEAKER_00]: And that never was a problem.
[SPEAKER_00]: And you have no say in that.
[SPEAKER_00]: What you have say in, is in gratuitously maintaining the ownership at face value of that which has been presented as myself.
[SPEAKER_00]: Failing to see that it's one of the aggregates, and as such, you're invisible to it, which means your very self doesn't know about you.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, how can it be yours?
[SPEAKER_00]: Learn how to let it endure, for as long as it wants to endure, whatever it is.
[SPEAKER_00]: Stop trying to get rid of it through your meditation technique.
[SPEAKER_00]: Stop trying to ignore it.
[SPEAKER_00]: Stop trying to distract yourself through sensuality.
[SPEAKER_00]: Just recognize what's there and allow it to endure.